## PROJECT 2 ENVIRONMENTAL SCIENTIST

Summary

Environmental Health and Safety Specialist with over 6 years of consulting experience specializing in regulatory and compliance support. Extensive knowledge of site assessments, permitting actions, filing compliance reports, and developing operations plans to comply with local, state, and federal regulations. Proven project management skills meeting deadlines under conditions of multiple demands and conflicting priorities.

## Skills

- CollaborationAgilityCritical thinkingProblem solving
- Responsive Project management

## Experience

Project 2 Environmental Scientist, Alamo Group, December 2021 - Current Selma, AL

- Manages 16 clients, including proposal development, project set up, financials and contract agreements to ensure quality deliverables are met on time, on budget, and in compliance.
- Interacts directly with clients, legal counsel, and regulatory agencies to ensure compliance.
- Works closely with a dozen or so team members to deliver project requirements, develop solutions, and meet deadlines.
- Reviews environmental data to determine pollution sources, offering remediation guidance.
- Supports scientists and engineers as subject matter expert on environmental regulations and policies.
- Facilitates environmental site assessments and recommends remediation plans.
- Serves as a technical specialist for a multiple projects, applying extensive knowledge of principals and practices within related fields.
- Delegates technical tasks to staff and project personnel, freeing up time to serve as a broad technical resource.

Project 1 Environmental Health and Safety Specialist, Maul Foster & Alongi Inc., December 2018 - December 2021 City, STATE

- Provided mentoring and direction to 15+ peers and junior staff.
- Preformed site inspections and compliance audits to develop and update site-specific environmental plans including Spill Prevention,
  Control, and Countermeasures Plans (SPCC), Stormwater Pollution Prevention Plans (SWPPP), Hazardous Waste Determinations.
- Conducted and project managed 15 Phase I Environmental Site Assessments (ESAs) to assess environmental concerns on subject properties.
- Oversaw a team of 20+ personnel during site development for a client that is listed as a Fortune 100 company.
- Prepared 8+ annual hazardous and dangerous waste reports.
- Created a regulatory compliance matrix to track local, state and federal requirements related to waste, hazardous waste, stormwater, and wastewater regulations.
- Conducted and designed indoor-air quality investigations.
- Managed \$700,000 dollars of project work. Ended year 2021 with approximately \$90,000 in net profit for the company.

Staff, Environmental Health and Safety Specialist, Maul Foster & Alongi Inc, December 2015 - December 2018 City, STATE

- Prepared lockout/tagout and confined space procedures for multiple different facilities.
- Prepared comprehensive plans, such as health and safety plans (HASPs), Chemical Hygiene Plans (CHP), and HM-232 plans, consistent with applicable regulations.
- Conducted ergonomics assessment using the Rapid Upper Limbs Assessment (RULA) and subsequently proposed alternative designs.
- Developed Process Safety Management (PSM) and Risk Management Plans (RMP) for anhydrous ammonia processes at several different facilities.
- Conducted Industrial Hygiene assessments by utilizing equipment to test for wide range of contaminates of concern (COCs).
- Assisted with fieldwork such as groundwater sampling, stormwater sampling, soil vapor sampling, soil sampling and hazardous building materials sampling.

Environmental Health and Safety Intern, Siltronic Corporation, June 2015 - December 2015 City, STATE

- Trained new employees in proper safety procedures to minimize accidents with proper behaviors
- Recommended measures to help protect workers from potentially hazardous work methods, processes, or materials
- Conducted an ergonomic assessment of an operations process and subsequently proposed an alternative design to reduce the risk of employee injuries
- Determined root causes of accidents via in-depth investigations and identified potential prevention strategies to mitigate future risk
- Collaborated with engineers to institute control or remedial measures for hazardous or potentially hazardous conditions or equipment
- Developed and maintained hygiene programs, including noise surveys, indoor air monitoring, and hazardous material management plans.

## **Education and Training**

Bachelor of Science Public Health, Environmental, Health and Safety,,, Oregon State University,, City State June 2015 Certifications

40-Hour Hazardous Waste Operations Training (HAZWOPER) OSHA 30-Hour Construction Industry Training Program RCRA Basic Hazardous Waste Training AHERA-Accredited Asbestos Building Inspector Certified Erosion and Sediment Control Lead Small-Water-System Operator, Oregon